Guide to the Bartlett Collection Pickitt Letters MS 054
Western Connecticut State University Archives and Special Collections
Bartlett Collection
1726-1906
1726-1806
Western Connecticut State University Archives and Special Collections
Bartlett, Stephen R., Dr., Jr.
Litchfield Historical Society
MS 054
0.25 Linear Feet 1 Box, 38 Folders
A collection of deeds and miscellany handed down from the Pickett Family which owned land in Danbury, CT among other places. The collection also contains a letter that describes the 1906 San Francisco earthquake.
Arrangement
Folders are arranged in chronological order and according to their original accession numbers applied by the Litchfield Historical Society.
Scope and Contents
With a few exceptions the folders of the collection contain single deeds between various parties and the Pickett (also spelled Pickit, Picket and Pickitt) family. Primarily they concern the properties of Ebenezer Pickett of Danbury, CT; there is the possibility that the Ebenezer Picketts in the deeds are different Ebenezers.
The collection contains one unidentified manuscript that details a home remedy or remedies and a letter to one of the Pickitt's ancestor's detailing the San Francisco earthquake of 1906.
Access Restrictions
Open for research without restrictions.
Biographical / Historical
The Pickett family were according to Thomas Robbins' history of Danbury from his "Century Sermon" of 1801, "The families of Picket, Knapp and Wildman are ancient families in the town." The Picketts were related through marriage to the Knapp, Benedict, Wildman, Seymour, Nichols, Barnum and Keeler families. Thomas Benedict (Ebenezer's cousin) who was the son of one of Danbury's first settlers was the 5th Justice of the Peace in Danbury and signed off on land transaction that occurred during his tenure.
There were at least 4 Ebenezer Picketts in the Danbury and New Milford areas in middle to late 1700s and according to the 1790 U.S. Census of Danbury, an Ebenezer Picket was the head of a household made up of 3 males under the age of 16, and 6 females, and Ebenezer Picket, jr. was over age 16 and lived with one female and was considered a "head of a household." An Ebenezer Pickett, Sr. as of the 1750s was a Danbury Town Selectman [pg. 586, Public Records of Connecticut, 1751-1757], along with fellow selectmen, Daniel Starr and Phineas Judd, expended out of Town stock 12 pounds in support of Ebenezer Barnum who was considered an "indigent person" whose lands were to being sold by order of the Connecticut General Assembly.
Many of the early deeds involve land on Chestnut Ridge (now in Bethel) overlooking the Danbury Township in the area around Chesnut Ridge Road, southeast of Danbury.
A genealogical chart of the Pickett family is included based in the most part on Truman Warner's research notes on early Danbury families Pickett Family Tree
Provenance
Dr. Stephen Bartlett, Jr. donated a "deed bag" and its contents to the Litchfield Historical Society in [1971?] - its accession number was 1971-93 - and the contents were donated to the WCSU Archivies by the Litchfield Historical Society in May 2011. To accompany the gift, Bartlett explained some of his genealogy as follows:
Ebenezer Pickett (or Pickitt) Jr. was from Danbury, CT. His son Rufus and wife Paulina Turrill came to Litchfield, CT and ran the Town Farm property on Bantam Lake in Morris, CT. Rufus bought a house on what is now route 109 on the high ground overlooking Bantam Lake and the Town Farm (aka the Pickett Farm). Their son, Alanson [Jasper] Pickett, had a daughter Julia who married Stephen R. Bartlett and their son Stephen R. Bartlett, Jr. donated this collection to the Litchfield Historical Society. Alanson Pickett's sister, Huldah Marinda Pickett married William H. Farnham in 1837 and came to the Farnham farm (Litchfield Co.). Pickett and Farnham's son Edwin Pickett Farnam had a daughter, Alice, from his first marriage who married her first cousin Stephen R. Bartlett Sr. Edwin Pickett Farnham second marriage was to Gertrude Richardson of Salem, MA.
Ebenezer Pickett, Jr. was the son of Ebenezer Pickett of Danbury who came to the area in the early 1700s.
The collection was presumably assembled by Dr. Setphen Bartlett, Jr.
Correspondence.; Danbury (Conn.) -- History.; Estate inventories; Maps.; Deeds; Danbury (Conn.); Bills of sale; San Francisco Earthquake and Fire, Calif., 1906; Pickett, Ebenezer; Pickett Family; Pickett, Ephraim; Pickett, Ebenezer, Jr.; Litchfield Historical Society
- Inventory
  - Deed - Ephraim Pickitt to Ebenezer Pickitt, Feb 1726 (Box 1, Folder 1971-93-1)
    General
    Transfer of 3 acres from Ebenezer's brother Ephraim on the Chestnutt Ridge above the town of Danbury.
  - Deed - Samuel Hayes to Ebenezer Pickit, Mar 1727 (Box 1, Folder 1971-93-2)
    Samual Hayes (Ebenezer's Father-In-Law) deeded to Ebenezer Pickit four and a half acres of land in the Township of Danbury in exchange for work Pickett had done for Hayes over the last year and a half.
  - Deed - Thomas Pickitt to Ebenezer Pickitt, Jan 31, 1738 (Box 1, Folder 1971-93-3)
    Ebenezer is Thomas' uncle. Deeded 2 pieces of land in Danbury making up 2 and a half acres - "the northerly part of the westerly Chestnut Ridge so called." And a one acre piece at Shelterock in Danbury - bounded westerly by the highway and southerly by Thomas' other land and northerly by his own land. Includes a sheet which appears to further explain the bouderies of the transaction.
  - Deed - Thomas Pickit to Ebenezer Pickit, Jan 3, 1738 (Box 1, Folder 1971-93-4)
    Thomas Pickit of New Milford received 40 shillings from brother Ebenezer Pickit of Danbury for two acres of [Division] land from the two (left ? Divisions] in Danbury. Signed by Thomas Picket, January 3, 1738/9.
  - Deed - Jacob Weed to Ebenezer Pickit, June 10, 1741 (Box 1, Folder 1971-93-5)
    Jacob Weed sold to Ebenezer Pickit for the sum of 30 pounds one piece of land in Danbury [fields?] that joined to land of Ebenezer Pickit on the north branch of Beaverbrook ("so called") and the western line, running from the Pickit's southwest corner along the bank south to Nichol's Corner and east to Benjamin Barnum's land and south by Weed's other land.
  - Deed - John Wood to James Pickit, June 14, 1742; [folder reads Wood, Jacob]. Deed is from a printed template. Very fragile. (Box 1, Folder 1971-93-6)
    Wood sells to Pickit for 10 pounds, "ten acres of [Division?] land to be taken up by James Pickit ??? any of the Common lands in the Township of Danbury out of the proabilion [prohibition?] lands in Danbury Town S."
  - Deed - Nathaniel Barnum to Ebenezer Pickit, September 16, 1742 (Box 1, Folder 1971-93-7)
    Payment of 40 pounds for 5 acres of land on Chesnut Ridge above the Town - bounded westerly by highway, notherly and easterly by his other lands southerly part by his own land and part by Hoyts land and part by land of Jacob Weed.
  - Letter - James Pickit to Joseph and Ebenezer Pickit, Feb 15, 1747 (Box 1, Folder 1971-93-8)
    Note requesting payment of 130 pounds to James' mother "when you shall receive the same for debt left with you."
  - Deed - Samuel Weed to Ebenezer Picket, October 4, 1748 (Box 1, Folder 1971-93-9)
    Payment of 40 shillings for 2 acres of land "to be laid out any where in Common and unbounded lands in Danbury Township excepting of prohibition lands."
  - Deed - Samuel Nicholds to Ebenezer Picket, Feb 9, 1749 (Box 1, Folder 1971-93-10)
    Payment of 133 pounds and 15 shillings for 13 acres of land "that lyeth northward for Chesnut [Ridge] bound southerly by Ebenezer Whits Land and easterly by Pickets Land and northerly by [Curtises?] Land..."
  - Deed - Daniel Stevens to Ebenezer Picket, Oct 8, 1753 (Box 1, Folder 1971-93-11)
    Payment of 30 pounds for "a quarter part of a forty eighth par of a right in my Common and undivided Lands in the Lower Seven miles in the Township of New Fairfield.
  - Obligation - Daniel Gray to Ebenezer Pickit, Mar 17, 1757 (Box 1, Folder 1971-93-12)
    Obligation of one hundred pounds of Daniel Gray of Dutchess County, NY to Ebenezer Pickit. More than 14 pounds (in NY currency) was paid to Pickit - "left with Ebenezer Pickit by James pickit formerly of Danbury ... for support of his mother, Hannah pickit widowed ... of James Pickit lately of Danbury. Deceased being the Mother in Law to the foresaid Daniel Gray and being inclined to live with Daniel..."
  - Deed - Ebenezer White to Ebenezer Pickit, Oct. 25, 1758 (Box 1, Folder 1971-93-13)
    Three and one-half acres for seven pounds (New York money) located in Danbury near Hayses Hill bound north by the land of the Boughtons, east by Ebenezer Pickit's own land, and west by highway or commond land.
  - Deed - Thomas Benedict to Ebenezer Pickit, Dec. 30, 1760 (Box 1, Folder 1971-93-14)
    Payment of 3 pounds 15 shillings one half right in the Common and undecided lands throughout Danbury Township.
  - Deed - Samuel Nickols to Ebenezer Pickit, Mar. 31, 1761 (Box 1, Folder 1971-93-15)
    Payment of "30 shillings worth of land to be taken up in the Clear Commons in Danbury according to the vote of the proprietors...."
  - Deed - Thomas Nobles to Ebenezer Pickit, Mar. 31, 1761 (Box 1, Folder 1971-93-16)
    Payment of 35 shillings lawful money for "all my right to the division of the land now to be laid out in the Clear Common in Danbury according to the vote of the proprietors of the Common and Undivided Lands....."
  - Daniel Starr to Ebenezer Pickit, May 6, 1761 (Box 1, Folder 1971-93-17)
    Payment of "41 shillings worth of land to be laid out anywhere in the Cleared Commons in Danbury being part of a Six pound Right Sale granted by vote of the priprietors of the Town....."
  - Deed - John Vidito to Ebenezer Pickit, Mar. 18, 1762 (Box 1, Folder 1971-93-18)
    Payment of 5 pounds 5 pence for "one acre of land lasting twenty rods lying in Danbury adjoining Pickit's land at the middle river so called bounded southerly by his Pickit's land, northerly by the river and Common Land, westerly by highway with two being .......out and the other inward."
  - Deed - Ebenezer Pickit, Jr. to Ebenezer Pickit, Dec. 21, 1768 (Box 1, Folder 1971-93-19)
    Three acres and three rods of land lying in Danbury at Hoyt's Clapboard Ridge in exchange for a piece of land at Mill Ridge containing one and a quarter acres together with the house and barn.
  - Bill of Sale - James Joyce to Ebenezer Pickit, Oct. 17, 1772 (Box 1, Folder 1971-93-20)
    Payment of seven pounds eighteen shillings, New York money, for household items such as a feather bed, blanket, pillows, sheets, platters, plates, etc.
  - Will - Daniel Pickit, Estate of, Apr. 22, 1776 (Box 1, Folder 1971-93-21)
    Two documents:
    Four pounds, four shillings and ten pence, one farthing to Daniel Pickit, son of Daniel Pickit. Signed by Ebenezer Pickit, guardian of father's estate.
    Equal third part of moveable estate and real estate to his wife, Dorcas Pickit.
  - Deed - Nathan Gregory, et al to Ebenezer Pickit, Jr., Mar. 20, 1781 and Mar. 21, 1781 (Box 1, Folder 1971-93-22)
    Sold thirty acres of land to Ebenezer Pickit, Junior, where his current house stands "beginning at a heap of stones at the highway at the southwest corner running easterly to a heap of stones and then running southerly to a stump with stones and bounded south and west by Ebenezer Pickit's land, then running northeasterly to a chestnut oak with stones to still the same course to a chestnut stump with stones to then running northerly to a beach stump with stones to the same course to a white oak tree with stones to bounded easterly by [Hea ? s] of Ephram Gregory and Ebenezer Gregory and Nathan Hoyt land then running west to a red oak tree with stones to then running south to a White Oak tree with stones to still the same course two rods to a stump with stones to bounded north by Matthew Boughton land and west by Matthew Linfley's land and highway then running easterly to a stump with stones to then running southerly to a heap of stones then running westerly to a chestnut stump with stones to the highway bounded southerly and westerly and northerly by Ebenezer Pickit's land then running southerly by highway to a heap of stones then southerly by highway to the first mentioned bounds."
    Sold four acres and three rods to "Ebenezer Pickit at Hayeshill, so called, beginning at the southeast corner to a heap of stones to highway running westerly by the highway to a heap of stones then still west to a heap of stones bounded northerly by Benjamin Knapp land then runing southerly to a heap of stones bounded west by Abraham Wildman land then running easterly to the first mentioned [bound?] bounded south by his son Ebenezer Pickit's land."
    Also sold two acres at "Hayeshill, so called, beginning at the southeast corner a heap of stones at the highway running northerly by highway to a heap of stones then still northerly by highway to an oak with stones to then running westerly to a heap of stones bounded north by Samuel Nichols land then southerly to a heap of stones bounded west by Benjamin Knapp land then east to the first mentioned [bound?] bounded south by highway."
    Also sold two acres of land at "Shelter Rock, so called, beginning at the south west corner a heap of stones at the highway running east to a heap of stones on the bank of the river then running northerly by the river to a heap of stones by the bank of the river then running west to a heap of stones then running southwesterly to highway southerly to the first mentioned [bound?] bounded south by Nathan Ketcham's land, north by Abraham Wildman's land.
    Also sold one acre and one rod "on the south side of Shelter Rock River beginning at a heap of stones on the bank of the river running southeast to a white ash with stones to then runing south to an elm tree with stones to then running easterly to a white ash tree with stones to then running still the same course to a white ash [staddle?] withstones to then running northwesterly to a heap of stones runing round by the riverplace and the river until it comes to the first mentioned [bounds?] bounded north by same aforementioned Nichols land and west by the river and on all other [?orts] by Matthew and Joseph Gregory's land."
  - Bill for services rendered to Samuel Nickols, Jan. 1782 (Box 1, Folder 1971-93-23)
    "Danbury January AD 1782. Samuel Nickols of Waterbury [deture?] for bordeing [boarding] and nursing wife Betsy ? tweelve weks [twelve weeks] and other services - L 02-16-14, D. Pell - L10 - 19 - 0 ......."
  - Receipts - Ebenezer Pickit, Estate of, and Daniel Pickit, Estate of, Jan. 10, 1785 and Mar. 14, 1787 (Box 1, Folder 1971-93-24 A)
    Two items:
    "Danbury March 14th, 1787. Received of Ebenezer Picket as he is Executor on the Estate of Ebenezer Pickit late of Danbury deceased, a note of hand in favour of said deceased against Matthew Lindsley dated 15th July 1782 payable the first of January 1784 for L7..17..3 lawful earning with interest ? paid; also 82 dollars in old Continental Bills, said to be the ....of the moveable estate of Daniel Pickit, deceased, which was distributed to his son Daniel, a minor, for whom I am now guardian, which Note of Bills are said to have been found among the papers of his deceased grandfather who was guardian to said minor; reviewed to account with the said minor." Signed by Benjamin Knapp.
    "Danbury January 10th, 1785. Then received of Ebenezer Pickit and Matthew Lindsley [Ex..} of Ebenezer Pickit deceasedthe sum of L17-14-9 1/2 which is the whole part and portion that was coming from the above aforesaid Ebenezer Pickit deceased Estate as appears by his Last will and testament to the heirs of his daughter Rebecca." Signed "Per? me, Thomas Brush, Gardean [Guardian]."
  - Inventories and Maps - Ebenezer Picket, Estate of, 1767-1803 (Box 1, Folder 1971-93-24 B)
    1. Inventory of items given to daughter Lois November 1767.
    2. Small booklet entitled "Great Plain" contains names with amount due or possibly amount paid.
    3. Small booklet, Inventory of moveables, May 20, 1787.
    4. Small booklet with "Ebenezar Pickets Book" on inside cover. Inventory of items advanced to his children Ebenezer, Calbe, Seymour, Rufus, Thomas, Sarah, Elizabeth, Mary, and Delilah as a portion of his estate.
    5. Outline of property: This piece as it is now marked off amounts to 18 acres and 34 rods of ground.
    6. Outline of property given to Ebenezer's children.
    7. Thomas Brush [guardian] receipt dated April 9th, 1790. Thirty five Schillings lawful money to be allowed on the part of Rebeckah Brush.
  - Inventories and Maps - Ebenezer Picket, Estate of, 1767-1803 (Folder 24 OS)
    1. Distribution of moveables and property.
    2. Distribution of moveables and property to the heirs of Daniel Picket out of their grandfather Ebenezer Picket's Estate: heirs of daughters Elisabeth (late wife to Samuel Nichols), Lois (late wife of Matthew Lindsley), Rebekca (late wife of Thomas Boughton).
    3. Outline of property with acreage, roods, and rods.
    4. Outline of properties: Hayes Hill, upper and lower; Shelter Rock; and, "A Plan of Ebenezer Picket's [Ri..h} Grounds.
  - Deed - Jared and Phebe Patchin to Ebenezer Pickit, Apr. 15, 1785 (Box 1, Folder 1971-93-25)
    Payment of 150 pounds, lawfull money, a "certain piece of land lying at the great plain, a place so called, in Danbury being our homestead lot and buildings the row standing and contains about six acres be it more or less bounded south by highway west, north, and east by land of Eli Boughton's."
  - Deed - Frederick J. Whiting and Ezra Starr to Ebenezer Picket, Jun. 8, 1785 (Box 1, Folder 1971-93-26)
    Bought for "Twelve Pounds ten shillings, Lawful Money, a piece of land lying in Danbury as Ten Acres so called, containing about one acre and a half, is bounded easterly and northerly by the Land belonging to the Heirs of Ebenezer Pickit, South by highway, west by Deacon Joshua Knaps Land."
  - Deed - Seamour Pickit to Ebenezer Pickit, May 6, 1793 (Box 1, Folder 1971-93-27)
    "....give to Ebenezer and his heirs and assigns forever one certain piece of land lying in said Danbury at Great Plain Bounded west on highway, North on Seamour Pickit land, East on the Heirs of Miles Boughton deceased, and South on aforementioed Heirs land being an orchard and containing about one acre be the same more or less as now staked out."
    No money exchanged for property.
  - Obligation - Seymour Pickit and Ebenezer Pickit to Peter Benedict, Feb. 25, 1797 (Box 1, Folder 1971-93-28)
    Obligation (bond) of one hundred dollars to be paid to Peter Benedict. Seymour Picket is guardian to Jsana Ketchum, a minor and under the age of 21. Jsana received a piece of land in Danbury from her mother Ruth Ketchum, "which lies at Beach Lott so called and contains ten acres and is bounded north on Seymour Pickits wife's Land - westerly on highway - southerly on land Russel? Bartlet and wife - easterly on Abijah Tuker? land."
    Seymour Pickit agreed to sell the land to Peter Benedict for "Fifty Dollers and Thirty Eight Cents and within nine months after Jsana becomes twenty one years, which will be in October 1805, produce and deliver a good and lawful Warrenter [Warranty?] Deed of the land and deliver it to Peter Benedict" without further expense. If Seymour and Ebenezer Picket fail to "produce and deliver said deed the obligation will remain in full force and virtue in law."
  - Deed - Seth Hall to Ebenezer Pickit, Jan. 18, 1798 (Box 1, Folder 1971-93-29)
    Payment of Nine Pounds Lawfull money for "one Eights Part of the Sawmill Standing on the Crost? Rivers [Cross River?] So Called adjoining the Land of Nehemuck? Beardsley."
  - Note - Ebenezer Pickit and Ebenezer Nichols to Daniel Comstock, Apr. 2, 1798 (Box 1, Folder 1971-93-30)
    "For Value Rec'd we the Subscribers Jointly and Severaley [separately] promis [promise] to pay Daniel Comstock Seventy four Dollars by the first day of November next with interest untill paid."
    Reverse side: "January of 1799. Rec'd on the within [written?] note forty Dollars by the hand of Mr. Ebenezer Nickols [and] Daniel Comstock."
  - Indenture - Ebenezer Picket to Friend Starr, Aug. 27, 1803 (Box 1, Folder 1971-93-31)
    "This indenture made this 27th Day of August AD 1803 between Friend Starr of Danbury....and Ebenezer Pickit of said Danbury....has this day put his Son Rufus: an Apprentice to the said Friend to learn the Art Trade or mystery of shoemaking & hereby ....the true & faithful service of said Rufus for the full Term of One year & Eleven Months wanting four days which Term will end on the 22nd day of July AD 1805......"
    Original document and transcription.
  - Home Remedies, n.d. [1750-1800] (Box 1, Folder 1971-93-32)
    "Recipe? for ointment. "take won [one] hanful [handful] of worm? [warm] wod? won [one] hanful [handful] of ru? won [one] hanful [handful] of suren? and won [one] hanful [handful] enehe [each] mah [make] it in Dear weed warter [water]."
    "won [one] ouce [ounce] of beter [butter], Pet [Put] Deuid? ito [into] Pinto [Pint?] Two Parts take won [one] half and slise [slice] it thin and put ito [into] half a Pint of warm over night. in the morning ? it out. Put in as much hunny [honey] or sugger [sugar] as will make into a surrup [syrup]. Put it over the fire. Bile [boil] very easley [easily]. ? [stir] it whil [while] billing [boiling]. skim it whi [while] Bitting [Boiling] Down to the thik wess [thickness] of new honny [honey] ? a sPun ful [spoonful] morning and eving [evening] while takeing [taking] thee aboue [above] mexsen [mixture?] for their constont [comfort]. Irink [Drink] tar? warter [water] for their constort [comfort]. Drink all four."
  - Receipt - Ebenezer Pickit to James Scott Smith, Mar. 5, 1804 (Box 1, Folder 1971-93-33)
    Payment of sixty dollars and eighteen cents to cover notes, bonds, claims, etc.
  - Promissory Note and Receipt - Ebenezer Picket to Jonathan Ingersoll, Mar. 7, 1805 (Box 1, Folder 1971-93-34)
    Promissory note for "twenty five dollars with interest."
    Receipt from Matthew Whittlsey, attorney for Jonathan Ingersoll, indicating promissory note was in hand signed by Ebenezer Pickit.
  - Deed - Caleb Pickit to Sarah Pickit, Aug. 6, 1806 (Box 1, Folder 1971-93-35)
    Payment of two hundred dollars for "two acres of meadow land lying in Danbury at Beaver brook so called bounded as follows - Southerly by Matthew Whittlesy ?ance, Easterly by Jacob W. Stewarts land, Northerly by Ebenezer Pickits land and Westerly by Jacob Sudas land."
  - Receipt - Rufus Picket to Levi Osborn, Jun. 2, 1808 (Box 1, Folder 1971-93-36)
    Payment to "Levi Osborn one pound and eight shillings and eleven pence whis [which is] to balance Ebenezer Pickets account up to this date."
    Reverse side:
    "Received of Ebonesior [Ebenezer] Pickett won [one] Load of wood which pays two dollars on th ?ith in receipt."
  - Court document - Hanson J. Pickett, Estate of, Jun. 29, 1881 (Box 1, Folder 1971-93-37)
    N. A Moore of Hartford, Connecticut, appointed by Stamford Probate Court to administer the Estate of Hanson J. Pickett of Darien, Connecticut.
  - Letter - Emily Raymond to Mrs. J. B. Bartlett, May 3, 1906 (Box 1, Folder 1971-93-38)
    Letter written by Emily Raymond, who lived in San Franciso, California, to her cousin, Mrs. J. B. Bartlett recounting the earthquake of 1906 and the aftermath.